Finding Aid for David Wheeler Palmer and family papers, 1807-1982
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
David Wheeler Palmer and family papers 1807-1982
Palmer, David Wheeler, 1807-1896.
852089 Aa 2; Ac
David Wheeler Palmer was a Bridgewater, Michigan school teacher and farmer. His papers consist of diaries, 1846-1864, 1876-1882, and 1887-1892, concerning daily activities and farm life. There are also papers of other family members, including Emmett Newton Palmer, a Brooklyn, Michigan physician, Fred E. Palmer, a surgeon who served in the Spanish-American War, and Louisa Palmer, who was a teacher in Hawaii.
3 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of various family members: Mrs. Marian Palmer Greene (donor no. 1546 ) beginning in 1941-1942; Louisa F. Palmer (donor no. 4720 ) in 1969; Ruth Palmer Beers (donor no. 4721 ) in 1969; and Mary E. Black (donor no. 10717 ) in 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The David W. Palmer collection, when originally received, was composed largely of the diaries of this Bridgewater Township farmer. Since then, other family papers have been added.
David W. Palmer was born in Connecticut, June 5, 1807. He moved to Lenox, New York in 1810. He was educated at Hamilton College. In October 1836, he came to Michigan and taught in Clinton, Michigan. Although he was a teacher, he also acquired 160 acres of government land to farm. He became active in the local community and when Bridgewater Township was first organized, Palmer became one of its officers and would hold the office of township clerk for thirty-six years, twenty-nine of them being consecutive. He was also justice of the peace nine years.
Emmett Newton Palmer (son of David W. Palmer) was an 1869 graduate of the University of Michigan Dept of Medicine and Surgery. He was a practicing physician in Brooklyn, Michigan.
Fred E. Palmer (son of Emmett N. Palmer) was an 1894 graduate of University of Michigan Dept of Medicine and Surgery. He was house surgeon at the University for two years and assistant to Dr. J. M. Marden for one year. He then established himself in Brooklyn, Michigan in private practice. With the outbreak of the Spanish-American War, Palmer, in May 1898, enlisted in the Thirty-third Michigan Regiment as hospital steward. He went to Cuba with his regiment and after the battle of Aguadores assisted in dressing wounds. He was then stationed at the hospital of Siboney until August, when he was sent to Fortress Monroe, in charge of the first boatload of wounded. Two weeks after landing he was called to Washington and discharged from the Thirty-third regiment by order of the Secretary of War. Surgeon General Sternberg then appointed him acting assistant surgeon to report to Camp Alger. Soon he was transferred to Camp Meade, and then to Summerville, South Carolina, where he remained until April, 1899, when he resigned and returned to his home. On Sept. 9, 1899, he received a telegram from Surgeon-General Sternberg, asking him to go to the Philippines as acting assistant surgeon. He telegraphed his acceptance, and three days later set sail for the Philippines. He arrived at his destination on Nov. 5, and on the 9th was assigned duty at the Santa Mesa hospital, where he remained with the exception of one month, during which time he was lecturer in the hospital of instruction at Manila. Fred Palmer would remain in the military serving until his retirement with disability in 1920.
Louisa Palmer (granddaughter of David W. Palmer) was a teacher and principal for 34 years of Hanahauoli School in Honolulu. She had lived in Hawaii since 1923. She retired in 1957, then she began researching her family's genealogy which resulted in the publication of "The Palmer Letters" based on the letters written by David Wheeler Palmer and other family members.
The David Wheeler Palmer collection consists mainly of his diaries and other papers. These diaries, dating from 1846 to 1892 with some gaps, comment in detail on his life, his family, the weather, financial transactions, and local politics. Other portions of the collection include materials of other family members: Palmer's wife Fidelia Randall Palmer; her brother Roswell Randall, Jr.; Emmett Palmer, the son of David and Fidelia; Fred Palmer, the son of Emmett; and Joseph Palmer, the father of David. Of interest are the photographs accumulated by Dr. Fred Palmer while he was serving in the Philippines. These include images of Hawaii on route to the Philippines and of the Santa Mesa facility in the Philippines. Another family member represented in the collection is Louisa Palmer who taught in Hawaii. She was an inveterate traveler who wrote extensive letters describing places visited for her students and family.
Subjects:
Agriculture--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Art.; Artists.; Bridgewater (Mich.); Brooklyn (Mich.); Clinton (Lenawee County, Mich.); Education--Michigan--Bridgewater.; Farm life--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Hanahau'oli School.; Hawaii.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1841-1850.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1851-1860.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1861-1870.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1871-1880.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1881-1890.; Michigan--Social life and customs--1891-1900.; Michigan--Social life and customs--19th century.; Palmer family.; Palmer, Emmett Newton.; Palmer, Fidelia Randall.; Palmer, Fred E.; Plamer, Louisa Fidelia.; Randall, Roswell.; Schools--Hawaii.; Spanish-American War, 1898.; Teachers--Hawaii.; Teachers--Michigan--Bridgewater.; Travelers.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bridgewater (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Carriages and coaches.; Dwellings--Michigan--Bridgewater.; Hawaii.; Palmer, David Wheeler, 1807-1896.; Palmer, Fred E.; Palmer, Fidelia.; Philippines.; Santa Mesa (Philippines); Spanish-American War, 1898.
Contributors:
Palmer, Emmett Newton.; Palmer, Fidelia Randall.; Palmer, Fred E.; Palmer, Louisa Fidelia.; Palmer, Russell Denison, 1818-1895.
Genre Terms:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- David Wheeler Palmer
  - Biographical sketch of David Wheeler Palmer written by Ara H. Palmer (Box 1)
  - Diaries
    - 1846, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1847, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1848, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - 1849 (Box 1)
    - 1850 (Box 1)
    - 1851 (Box 1)
    - 1852 (Box 1)
    - 1853 (Box 1)
    - 1854 (Box 1)
    - 1855 (Box 1)
    - 1856 (Box 1)
    - 1857 (Box 1)
    - 1858 (Box 1)
    - 1859 (Box 1)
    - 1860 (Box 1)
    - 1861 (Box 1)
    - 1862 (Box 1)
    - 1863 (Box 1)
    - 1864 (Box 1)
    - July 8, 1876-March 18, 1878, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - November 13, 1879-January 29, 1882, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - July 23, 1887-November 23, 1890, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - November 24, 1890-February 7, 1892, 1 volumes (Box 1)
- Family papers
  - Letters exchanged among various family members
    - 1813-1835 (Box 1)
    - 1836-1840 (Box 1)
    - 1841-1845 (Box 1)
    - 1846-1888 (Box 1)
    - 1835-1901, 3 folders (Box 1)
      (2012 accession)
    - Undated (Box 1)
  - Business and legal records 1834-1901 (Box 1)
  - Receipts and other financial material (Box 1)
  - Palmer family clippings (Box 1)
  - Photograph of Palmer home in Bridgewater, 1881 (Box 1)
- Other family members
  - Joseph Palmer (father of D. W. Palmer) account book 1807-1838 (Box 2)
  - Russell D. Palmer account books (Box 2)
    (also include biographical material)
  - Fidelia Randall Palmer (wife of D. W. Palmer)
    - Autograph book 1836-1854 (Box 2)
    - Scrapbooks 1870s-1890s, 3 volumes (Box 2)
  - Roswell Randall, Jr. (composer; brother of Fidelia Palmer). Musical compositions and arrangements, 3 volumes (Box 2)
  - Emmett N. Palmer (son of D. W. and Fidelia Palmer)
    - Account book 1890s (Box 2)
    - Medical notebook, University of Michigan Dept of Medicine and Surgery 1863, undated (Box 2)
    - Account book 1869-1870 (Box 2)
      (include text for a Sunday message)
  - Fred Palmer (son of Emmett N. Palmer) photographs of the Philippines and Hawaii, circa 1900, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Account book 1872-1877 (Box 2)
- Louisa F. Palmer
  - "Autobiography of Louisa Fidelia Palmer: The Beginning" (Box 3)
  - Biographical (Box 3)
  - Photographs (Box 3)
  - Personal miscellaneous (Box 3)
  - Travel letters
    - World trip 1931 (Box 3)
    - Europe 1952, 1953 (Box 3)
    - Japan 1954, 1960, 1969 (Box 3)
    - Europe 1957 (Box 3)
    - Mexico and Guatemala 1959 (Box 3)
    - Europe 1961 (Box 3)
    - World trip 1964 (Box 3)
    - Travel letters 1974 (Box 3)
  - Letters to Hanahauoli School (Box 3)
  - Printed Christmas letters and travel letters sent to the children of Hanahauoli 1945-1979, 1 volumes (Box 3)
  - Loose material from volume (Box 3)
  - "The Palmer Letters" research and related
    - Letters received from those who received a copy of the volume (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous drafts of typescripts of letters from volume and related (Box 3)
Related Material
The library also has in its printed holdings a volume entitled "The Palmer Letters" privately printed by Louisa Fidelia Palmer in 1963. This volume includes genealogical information and transcriptions of many of the family letters and diary entries.